Guide to the Neill Compton Wilson Papers, 1944-1969
Department of Special Collections
Neill Compton Wilson Papers,
1944-1969
Special Collections M0182
Wilson, Neill Compton, 1899-
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restricted access: requires 24 hour paging period.
Provenance
Gift of Neill C. Wilson, 1969.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, documents, and original typescripts. Collection covers the origins, planning, research, writing, and publication of N. Wilson's novels, with emphasis on those published after 1963: DEEPDOWN RIVER, GALLEON BAY, and THE FEUDING POSTMASTERS. Also included are items relating to copyright procedure.
Container List
Figures in parentheses indicate number of items in category; dates indicate earliest and latest items in category, and are not necessarily inclusive.
- Miscellaneous, 1951 - 1968,containing: (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical data on Wilson
  - Correspondence between Wilson and his agents, including Brandt and Brandt, A. M. Heath and Co., and Littauer and Wilkinson, 1951 - 1968, (31).
  - Correspondence between Wilson and his publishers, Henry Holt and Co. and William Morrow and Co., 1951 - 1968, (31).
    Includes letters, royalty statements, and printed notices.
  - Miscellaneous business correspondence, 1951 - 1963, (7).
  - Printers' notices and reviews.
  - Correspondence with readers, 1950 - 1966, (23).
  - Copyrights, 1955 - 1961, (4).
  - Correspondence with the Saturday Evening Post and the Readers' Digest, 1951 - 1962, (16).
  - Research, n.d., 1959, 1961, (3).
  - Items on professional writing, 1963 - 1967, (4).
- The Nine Brides and Granny Hite, including: (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Items on the origins of the story and research.
  - Early notes.
  - Correspondence with the publisher, William Morrow and Co., 1958 - 1967, (3).
  - Other correspondence, including contract for television rights, 1952 - 1968, (10).
  - Reviews and letters from readers, 1950 - 1954, (41).
  - Royalty statements and miscellaneous business letters.
- Deepdown River, including: (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Items on the origins of the novel and research.
  - Two early typescript versions of Chapter 32, originally a short story entitled, The Calling Of Link Yawkey.
  - Correspondence with the publisher, William Morrow and Co., 1963 - 1965, (22).
  - Miscellaneous business letters, primarily permissions, 1964 - 1965, (9).
  - Reviews and letters from readers, 1964 - 1965.
  - Items on copyright search, including note by Wilson on the Importance of Obtaining a Copyright On Assignment Upon Publication of a Magazine Story.
- Galleon Bay, including: (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Items on the origins, research, planning, and copyrights of the book, 1960 - 1967.
- Galleon Bay, including: (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with the publisher, William Morrow and Co., 1967 - 1968, (50).
  - Miscellaneous business correspondence, 1967, (3).
  - Reviews and letters from readers, 1968.
- Galleon Bay, including: (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Data on the proposed Pacific Gas and Electric nuclear power plant at Bodega Bay. Used as research material for this novel.
- Galleon Bay, including: (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Pacific Gas and Electric, Preliminary Hazards Summary Report, Bodega Bay Atomic Park, Unit Number 1, December 28, 1968.Used as research material for the novel.
- Galleon Bay, including: (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pacific Gas and Electric, Statement with Respect To Its Proposed Bodega Bay Atomic Park, Unit Number 1, October 23, 1964.Used as research material for the novel.
- Galleon Bay, including: (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - First drafts.
- Galleon Bay, including: (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Final copy with publisher's over-editings, as sent to printer.
- Galleon Bay, including: (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Printer's galley-proofs, with copyreader's and author's corrections.
- The Feuding Postmasters, including: (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Items on the origins and planning of the novel.
  - Partial typescript work draft.
  - Copyright material.
- The Feuding Postmasters, including: (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Typescript final draft.
  - Correspondence with his agent, Littauer and Wilkinson, 1967, (12).
  - Correspondence with his publisher, William Morrow and Co., 1967 - 1968, (32).
  - Business correspondence and letters from readers. (To be added).
- The Feuding Postmasters, including: (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Printer's working copy.
- The Feuding Postmasters, including: (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Printer's copy read proofs.
- St. John of Bohemia, Bohemian Grove Play, 1969,including: (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1966 - 1969, (18).
  - Original typescript.
  - Final script, xerox copy.
- Binder # 13, containing newstand editions, or xerox copies, and copyright documents of the following short stories, which were subsequently brought together as seven of the fourteen chapters of The Nine Brides and Granny Hite: (dates refer to the issue of The Saturday Evening Post in which they appeared) (Othertype Oversize)
  - Mountain Woman, January 17, 1948
  - The Devil's Daughter, April 16, 1949
  - Granny Hite vs. The United States, March 25, 1950
  - Do You Take This Woman?, May 13, 1950
  - Granny Hite and the Angry Mob, December 23, 1950
  - The Bashful Daughter, February 24, 1951
  - Granny Hite and the Spirit Of `76, March 8, 1952
- Binder # 14, containing newstand editions, or xerox copies, and copyright documents of the following short stories, which were subsequently brought together as elements of the novel, Deepdown River: (Othertype Oversize)
  - The Red-Centered Quilt Liberty, March 23, 1946
  - He Loves Me Colliers, June 15, 1946
  - Moment Of Peril Saturday Evening Post, October 12, 1946
  - Stranger On the River Saturday Evening Post, September 12, 1959
  - The Real Champion Country Gentleman, October 1962
  - The Bugles and Gideon Lee Colliers, May 22, 1948
  - Deadline For Dynamite Saturday Evening Post, February 24, 1962
  - The Wolf She Howl Blue Book, January 1952
  - Whistle Across the Valley Liberty, November 11, 1944
  - The Dancing Steamboat Saturday Evening Post, January 4, 1947
- Binder # 15, containing newstand editions and xerox copies, and copyright documents of the following short stories, which subsequently were contributing elements to the novels Galleon Bay and The Feuding Postmasters: (Othertype Oversize)
  - The Skiff Beneath the Alder Saturday Evening Post, April 29, 1961
  - The Unveiling of Ad Dabner Saturday Evening Post, March 9, 1946
  - The Lady In the Doorway Saturday Evening Post, August 10, 1946
  - Ovid Rings the Bell Saturday Evening Post, March 22, 1947
  - Sea-gull Express This Week (San Francisco Chronicle), July 30, 1944
- Works Of Neill C. Wilson:
  - The Nine Brides and Granny Hite, William Morrow and Co., 1952,inscribed by the author All the affection in the world to Elsie and Clarence, Neill C. Wilson.
  - Here Is the Golden Gate, William Morrow and Co., 1962.
  - Deepdown River, William Morrow and Co., 1964.
  - Galleon Bay, William Morrow and Co., 1968.
  - The Feuding Postmasters, William Morrow and Co., 1969.
  - St. John Of Bohemia, Bohemian Club, 1969.